Survey of the Francis Underhill Macy papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Francis Underhill Macy papers
1983-2007
2010C40
Hoover Institution Archives
16 manuscript boxes (6.4 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, meeting materials, notes, lists, memoranda, printed matter, and photographs, relating to nongovernmental exchange programs between Americans and citizens of the Soviet Union and its successor republics, and to promotion of Gestalt psychology, environmentalism, nuclear safety and alternative energy sources in the Soviet Union and its successor republics.
Macy, Francis Underhill, 1927-2009
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2010.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1927 Born, Evanston, Illinois
1949 B.A., Government, Wesleyan University
1951 M.A., Slavic Studies, Harvard University
1953 Married Joanna Rogers
1961 Led citizen diplomatic mission to the Soviet Union
1963 Present at the March on Washington
1964-1972 Served as deputy Peace Corps director in India, country director in Tunisia and Nigeria, and as director of all Peace Corps programs in Africa
circa 1980s Director, Association for Humanistic Psychology
1991 With Enid Schreibman, founded Center for Safe Energy
1995-2009 Co-director, Center for Safe Energy
1995- Director, Institute for Deep Ecology
2005 Awarded Nuclear Free Future Lifetime Achievement Award
2009 Death
Scope and Content of Collection
The Francis Underhill Macy papers include correspondence, reports, meeting materials, notes, lists, memoranda, printed matter, and photographs related to nongovernmental exchange programs between Americans and citizens of the Soviet Union and its successor republics, and to promotion of Gestalt psychology, environmentalism, nuclear safety and alternative energy sources in the Soviet Union and its successor republics.
Francis Underhill Macy was an environmentalist who organized exchange programs between the United States and the Soviet Union. The collection has been kept in its original order, with the Chronological File comprising the majority of the materials. Materials from the 1980s and early 1990s consist mostly of files on exchange programs, including documentation of Macy’s trips to the Soviet Union and his work for the Association for Humanistic Psychology. In addition to exchange program files, later materials include documentation of Macy’s work for various environmental groups and files on environmental conferences.
Association for Humanistic Psychology.; Center for Safe Energy.; Energy policy--Former Soviet republics.; Energy policy--Soviet Union.; Environmental protection--Former Soviet republics.; Environmental protection--Soviet Union.; Former Soviet republics--Relations--United States.; Nuclear energy.; Psychology.; Soviet Union--Relations--United States.; United States--Relations--Former Soviet republics.; United States--Relations--Soviet Union.
- Chronological File, 1983-1997, 2006
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes correspondence, itineraries, clippings, meeting minutes, circulars, notes, conference materials, memoranda, applications, and photographs related to exchange programs between the United States and Soviet Union and various environmental projects. Includes documents related to trips organized by the Association for Humanistic Psychology, Interhelp, the Center for US-USSR Initiatives (CUUI), and the National Council for International Visitors.
  Materials from the 1980s and early 1990s document exchange programs, including Macy’s trips to the Soviet Union, and his work for the Association for Humanistic Psychology. Later materials include documentation on various environmental projects.
  - 1983-1986 (Box 1)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - 1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - 1988, 1991 (Box 4)
  - 1989 (Box 5)
  - 1989-1990 (Box 6)
  - 1990 (Box 7)
  - 1991, 1995-1996 (Box 8)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 9)
  - 1991-1994 (Box 10)
  - 1992 (Box 11)
  - 1993, 1998 (Box 12)
  - 1998-1999, 2006 (Box 13)
  - 1996 (Box 14)
  - 1996-1997 (Box 15)
  - 1996-1997 (Box 16)
- Psychology File, 1982-1990 (Box 13)
  Printed matter, notes, and correspondence related to psychology. Includes a notebook on Soviet psychologists.